<?xml version = '1.0' encoding = 'UTF-8'?>
<!DOCTYPE document PUBLIC "-//APACHE//DTD Documentation V1.3//EN" "document-v13.dtd">
<document>
  <header>
    <title>The disambiguation file sme-dis.rle</title>
  </header>
  <body>
    <section id="The_disambiguation_file_sme-dis.rle" >
      <title>The disambiguation file sme-dis.rle</title>
      <section id="File_macrostructure" >
        <title>File macrostructure</title>
        <p>The disambiguation file sme-dis.rle consists of the following parts:</p>
        <ul>
          <li>Delimiter declarations</li>
          <li>Tag and tag list declarations</li>
          <li>Constraints</li>
        </ul>
        <p>The file format is documented in Tapanainen 1996. Cf. also the <link href="cgii-usage.html" >general discussion on CG-2 usage</link>.</p>
        <section id="The_delimiters" >
          <title>The delimiters</title>
          <p>Three sentence delimiters are declared, &quot;.&quot;, &quot;?&quot; and &quot;!&quot;.</p>
        </section>
        <section id="Tag_and_tag_list_declarations" >
          <title>Tag and tag list declarations</title>
          <p>This section consists of two parts. In the first part, every single lexc tag has been given a list declaration of its own. There probably is a better way of doing this (the reader is invited to find a better way :-).</p>
          <p>In the second part comes the real set and list declarations.</p>
        </section>
        <section id="The_constraints" >
          <title>The constraints</title>
          <p>The constraints are organised in cycles. CG-2 makes it possible to arrange the rules in blocks. Each set of constraints is introduced with the key word CONSTRAINTS, and the last section is closed off with the word END.</p>
          <p>First we have disambiguation rules that each refer to one single cohort (marked with &quot;cycle 0&quot;). Then comes local disambiguation, referring mainly to words one cohort to the left or right (possibly with intervening adverbials) (&quot;cycle 1&quot;). Then follows the main part of the disambiguation file (&quot;cycle 2&quot;),which contains rules with local and long-distance scope. Finally, there is a cycle consisting of rules with global scope, along with some rules that need to come as late as possible (&quot;cycle 3&quot;).</p>
          <p>The rules within some of the main cycles are organised in subcycles, set apart by the key word CONSTRAINTS. This gives better control of the order in which the rules apply.</p>
          <p>Also note that rules are often organised such that a block of rules is followed by a set of examples. In these cases, the first rule will go with the first example, the second rule with the second example, and so on. The idea is that this gives a better overview than if each rule is immediately followed by an example.</p>
          <p>The majority of the examples show where a rule hits. But in some cases, the example shows where the rule does NOT hit. Then the example is there to illustrate the need for some specific condition in the rule. Which condition is normally pointed out explicitly.</p>
        </section>
      </section>
      <section id="More_on_the_cycles" >
        <title>More on the cycles</title>
        <section id="Cycle_0" >
          <title>Cycle 0</title>
          <p>Much cohort-internal disambiguation is taken care of in the preprocessor phase (in the script <link href="docu-lookup2cg.html" >lookup2cg</link>, see also the documentation in the script).</p>
          <p>The rules in this section are there to reject analyses where there is a better analysis in the same cohort. Typically, this is the case where a lexicalised derivation competes with a dynamically derived form. For example, adverbs derived from adjectives are rejected if there is an alternative analysis with the lexicalised adverb.</p>
          <p>Names are preferred to ordinary nouns if the word-form has initial capital and occurs in the middle of a sentence.</p>
        </section>
        <section id="Cycle_1" >
          <title>Cycle 1</title>
          <p>This cycle consists of two subcycles. In cycle 1a we deal with some personal pronouns that have homonyms in other parts of speech, we pick out some Px readings, and select verb readings that depend on personal pronouns. There are also two rules related to &quot;ahte&quot;, which have to come early so that only the CS reading of &quot;ahte&quot; survives to cycle 2. In cycle 1b most of the remaining Px readings are removed.</p>
        </section>
        <section id="Cycle_2" >
          <title>Cycle 2</title>
          <p>This is the largest cycle in the disambiguation file. It consists of several subcycles. The main organising principle is that rules that are relevant to one and the same part of speech should come as one rule block. However, some exceptions to this principle have turned out to be necessary. For example, although the main verb rule block follows the main noun rule block, certain verb rules precede the noun rules, thereby improving the effect of the latter.</p>
          <p>In the following, the main subcycles of Cycle 2 are dealt with one by one.</p>
          <section id="Noun_or_not" >
            <title>Noun or not?</title>
            <p>In this subcycle some relatively certain noun readings are picked out. In most cases adjective readings are thereby removed, but also some verb readings. The selected noun readings will serve as context for later rules.</p>
          </section>
          <section id="Adjectives_and_adverbs" >
            <title>Adjectives and adverbs</title>
            <p>In this subcycle some relatively certain adverb and adjective readings are picked out. The competing readings are verb or noun readings.</p>
          </section>
          <section id="Disambiguating_clitics" >
            <title>Disambiguating clitics</title>
            <p>So far one rule here. It removes the Qst reading from adverbs like &quot;nugo&quot;.</p>
          </section>
          <section id="Disambiguating_adpositions" >
            <title>Disambiguating adpositions</title>
            <p>Two subcycles. The first one deals with adpositions of the GASKAL class, in the cases where they combine with a coordination. The rules look OK, but they cannot at this point be tested against the corpus (no potential hits). The second subcycle consists of rules that select and remove Po and Pr readings in a general fashion. The ordering of rules is crucial here. The present ordering is not necessarily the best one, although it has been worked on quite a lot.</p>
          </section>
          <section id="Disambiguating_subjunctions" >
            <title>Disambiguating subjunctions</title>
            <p>Two subcycles. The first one contains two general CS rules and a number of rules related to individual subjunctions with homonyms in other POS. The second one contains rules that disambiguate those ambiguous instances that survive the first subcycle.</p>
          </section>
          <section id="Disambiguating_adverbs" >
            <title>Disambiguating adverbs</title>
            <p>Consists of some general adverb rules (SELECT and REMOVE), some rules that distinguish between adverbs and other specified POS, and a series of rules related to individual adverbs. The latter set of rules deals with ambiguities that are not resolved by the general adverb rules.</p>
          </section>
          <section id="Disambiguating_pronouns" >
            <title>Disambiguating pronouns</title>
            <p>Since personal pronouns are dealt with in cycle 1, this cycle consists of rule blocks for interrogative pronouns, reflexive pronouns, reciprocal pronouns, ordinals (in practice &quot;nubbi&quot;), indefinite pronouns, and demonstrative pronouns, in that order, so that the rules for demonstratives, for example, can build on the output of all other pronoun rules.</p>
            <p>Note that there are particularly many rules for &quot;dat&quot;, since &quot;dat&quot; can be a demonstrative pronoun or a personal pronoun. We have chosen here to treat &quot;dat&quot; as a personal pronoun whenever it stands alone.</p>
          </section>
          <section id="Disambiguating_adjectives" >
            <title>Disambiguating adjectives</title>
            <p>This cycle is introduced by some rules for individual adjectives, followed by some rules that pick out comparatives. The next block of rules identify attributes that come between a demonstrative and a noun with compatible cases. Between these elements we expect only DP-internal material, so it is relatively easy to identify attributes in this domain. It is much harder to identify attributes that are not preceded by demonstratives, which is why the next rule block, for other attribute rules, is much longer. After the main rule block for attributes follow rules for coordinated attributes and for &quot;buorre&quot;. The last part of the adjective cycle contains rules for predicative adjectives, and finally, a couple of adverb rules.</p>
          </section>
          <section id="Disambiguating_verbs_-_part_1" >
            <title>Disambiguating verbs - part 1</title>
            <p>In this cycle we deal with some verbs that are relatively easy to disambiguate. We select ConNeg and imperative forms, and also some infinitives. In addition, in the middle of the rule block for infinitives there are also some rules that remove infinitive. Finally we select some PrfPrc readings, including cases where &quot;leamaš&quot; appears without a finite verb, some Actios, and some finite forms of auxiliary &quot;orrut&quot;.</p>
          </section>
          <section id="Disambiguating_nouns" >
            <title>Disambiguating nouns</title>
            <p>The first rules in this cycle deal with proper nouns. Then follow a series of rules that remove certain adjective readings when corresponding noun readings are available. After that the case disambiguation begins. For each case there is a rule section with the following structure: 1) rules that identify single occurences of the case in question, 2) rules that find coordinated elements with that case, 3) rules that REMOVE that case in certain environments. This is to make the job easier for later case rules, by removing wrong readings as early as possible.</p>
<p>Since there are quite a few syntactic environments where only genitive case is found, we pick out genitive readings first. Then nominative rules follow, and after that accusative.</p>
          </section>
          <section id="Disambiguating_verbs_-_part_2" >
            <title>Disambiguating verbs - part 2</title>
          </section>
          <section id="Residual_cases" >
            <title>Residual cases</title>
          </section>
        </section>
        <section id="Cycle_3" >
          <title>Cycle 3</title>
          <p>Trond Trosterud/Marit Julien</p>
          <p>
<!-- hhmts start -->Last modified: Tue Dec 28 12:21:18 2004 <!-- hhmts end -->          </p>
        </section>
      </section>
    </section>
  </body>
</document>
