<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE document PUBLIC "-//APACHE//DTD Documentation V2.0//EN"
"http://forrest.apache.org/dtd/document-v20.dtd">
<document>
  <header>
    <title>The sme Makefile and scripts</title>

    <authors>
      <person email="trond.trosterud@hum.uit.no" name="Trond Trosterud" />
    </authors>
  </header>

  <body>
    <section>
      <title>The sme Makefile and scripts</title>

      <p>The Makefile is used to compile the source files, i.e. to make the
      programs. It is put to use by (being in <code>gt/sme/src/</code> and)
      writing the command <code>make</code>. Makefiles in general are
      documented in introductions to the program <code>make</code>, and the
      format of the makefiles used in this project is found in Appendix C of
      the Beesley and Karttunen book. The makefiles for the other languages
      follow the same layout, but they are simpler.</p>

      <section>
        <title>The Makefile itself</title>

        <p>The sme Makefile is organized as follows: It contains of a number
        of blocks, each block builds one binary file. Each binary file is
        dependent upon a number of other files. The first line of each block,
        the dependency line, mentions the target file, a colon, and the
        address of the dependency file. On the next line comes the file with
        address, thereafter again a colon, and after the colon the dependency
        files are listed. The dependency line can go over several lines with
        the backslash character (\). In the first block, the dependency lines
        look as follows:</p>

        <source>isme.fst: ../bin/isme.fst
../bin/isme.fst: ../bin/sme.fst ../bin/sme.save ../bin/tok.fst \
        ../bin/allcaps.fst
</source>

        <p>After the dependency line comes the actions themselves. In the
        Makefile, each line is initiated with a TAB character. Commands are
        initiated with the "@" character, and arguments delimited with quotes.
        Quotes within the quotes are preceded by \.</p>

        <p>The commands are initiated by an informative banner printed to the
        screen. Then comes the actions. They are printed to a temporary script
        file (in the first block, the file is "isme-fst-script", by the
        @printf command. Then the relevant program (e.g. the program xfst in
        the first block of the sme Makefile) reads the scriptfile and executes
        it. Finally, the temporary script file is removed by the @rm command.
        The makefiles for the other languages are made in the same way.</p>

        <p>Note that the source files are taken from the src directory (and
        referred to by filenames only, since the Makefile itself is in the src
        directory), whereas the binary files are taken from the bin directory,
        and hence prefixed with '../bin/'.</p>

        <section>
          <title>lookup: the lookup scripts</title>

          <p>There are three lookup scripts (i.e. scripts for the Xerox
          program <code>lookup</code>) in the bin directory, cap-sme,
          guess-sme and missing. They are all invoked with the lookup -f flag,
          i.e. when the ordinary parser is called as in 1., the script version
          is called as in 2the.:</p>

          <ol>
            <li>... | lookup -flags mbTT -utf8 bin/sme.fst | ...</li>

            <li>... | lookup -flags mbTT -utf8 -f bin/cap-sme | ...</li>
          </ol>

          <p>The general format of the Xerox lookup scripts is documented in
          the chapter on lookup in the Beesley and Karttunen book. To take one
          example, the script missing looks like this (for the user
          <code>trond</code>, the Makefile generates scripts with a unique
          absolute path for each user):</p>

          <source>analyzer /Users/trond/gt/sme/bin/sme.fst
 foreign /Users/trond/gt/sme/bin/foreign.fst
 typos /Users/trond/gt/sme/bin/typos.fst

 analyzer
 foreign
 typos</source>

          <p>The script names three transducers (by arbitrary names), and
          gives an absolute path to each of the transducers. Then comes an
          empty line, and then the transducers, in the order they are meant to
          apply.</p>

          <p>The main point with the scripts is that it is possible to chunk
          different transducers together, without making one large transducer.
          The main drawback with them is that they are much slower than simple
          transducers. The script cap-sme makes it possible to analyse words
          written with capital letters, but if you want to analyse a larger
          text with this script, you should rather issue the command before
          lunch break, and then return after lunch to have a look at what has
          happened.</p>

          <p>Since these scripts need a user-unique path, involving the user
          name, they must be generated in the makefile. This is done as
          follows (using the same script as example):</p>

          <source>missing: ../bin/missing
../bin/missing:
        @echo
        @echo "*** Generating missing ***";
        @echo
        @printf "analyzer ${BINDIR}/sme.fst\n\                                                                                             
        foreign ${BINDIR}/foreign.fst\n\                                                                                                   
        typos ${BINDIR}/typos.fst\n\n\                                                                                                     
        analyzer\n\                                                                                                                        
        foreign\n\                                                                                                                         
        typos\n" &gt; $@</source>

          <section>
            <title>The cap-sme script</title>

            <p>This script chunks the transducers sme.fst and allcap.fst,
            i.e., it analyses both biilla, Biilla and BIILLA (but not
            BiilLA).</p>
          </section>

          <section>
            <title>The guess-sme script</title>

            <p>This script involves the transducers sme.fst (the ordinary sme
            transducer) and g-sme.fst (the guesser). </p>

            <fixme author="Tomi">It is unclear to what extent this script
            works.</fixme>
          </section>

          <section>
            <title>The missing script</title>

            <p>The script itself was quoted in the introductory text above.
            The idea behind the script is to first run the incoming text
            through the ordinary sme transducer, then to run it through an
            extensive list of foreign (i.e. Norwegian, Swedish, Finnish and
            English) word forms, and then to run it through a list of known
            typos, both typos that we know are common, and typos that we have
            attested in our corpora. A typical command involving this script
            is the following:</p>

            <source>cat corp/ntunix corp/*txt | preprocess --abbr=bin/abbr.txt | 
 lookup -flags mbTT -utf8 -f bin/missing | grep '\?' | 
 cut -f1 | sort | uniq -c | sort -nr | less</source>

            <p>Here, the text is preprocessed as usal. Then it is lead to the
            missing script, and all wordforms that are either Såmi words,
            Norwegian etc. words or known typos, get an analysis. The
            remaining words (the ones picked out with the <code>grep '\?'
            </code>command) are the words really missing from the transducer
            (thereby the name of the script).</p>
          </section>
        </section>

        <section>
          <title>The preprocessor</title>

          <p>The sme Makefile contains target for generating a file
          <code>abbr.txt</code> which contains a list of abbreviations used in
          the preprocessing phase. The file is generated by script
          <code>abbr-extract</code> which is located in <code>gt/script</code>
          directory. It gets as a command line parameter the main abbreviation
          file and then a list of files from where multiword expressions
          should be searched for. Basically:</p>

          <source>abbr.txt: ../bin/abbr.txt
../bin/abbr.txt: ../../script/abbr-extract abbr-sme-lex2.txt \
        propernoun-sme-lex.txt closed-sme-lex.txt adv-sme-lex.txt

        abbr-extract --abbr_lex=abbr-sme-lex2.txt \
        --lex=propernoun-sme-lex.txt,closed-sme-lex.txt,adv-sme-lex.txt \
        --output=../bin/abbr.txt
</source>
        </section>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>If one ever should need to manage without make...</title>

        <p>In case the actual commands themeselves are sometimes needed: This
        is a list of the commands that were needed to build a morphological
        parser before the time of the makefile.</p>

        <source>exchange "sme" for other lg (smj, sms)

Compiling the parser
====================

in twolc (open by typing "twolc")
---------------------------------
read-grammar twol-sme.txt
compile
save-binary twol-sme.bin

in lexc (open by typing "lexc")
-------------------------------
compile-source *-sme.txt
or: run-script skript1 (smj has script file "lskr", sms has no script file)
read-rules twol-sme.bin
compose-result
save-result sme.save

in xfst (open by typing "xfst")
-------------------------------
load stack caseconv.fst
load stack sme.save
compose net
save stack sme.fst

The tok.fst tokenizer is also built in xfst:
--------------------------------------------
read-regex &lt; case.regex
save stack caseconv.fst
</source>
      </section>

      <p class="last_modified">Last modified: $Date$, by
      $Author$</p>
    </section>
  </body>
</document>